Let's see where we left off
last week.   Let's
go there.  We upload
computer systems.  Okay.
Installing operating systems.
Okay, just
a moment.  Okay, perfect.
Okay.  Main operating systems.
Okay.
Okay.  Okay.  Very good.
This is unit two.
Types of operating systems.  Okay.  And
we're going to look at applications
and, oh, licenses.  Momentin.  Types of
licenses.  Oh, just a moment.  Wait.
Installation procedure.  Oh,
wait, we already did this.  Okay,
so I'll leave this.
Bootloaders, right?
Virtualization technologies.
We were looking at Virtual Box.
Preliminary considerations.
Facility.  Okay.  Okay.
Installing applications.  My SQL.
Very good.  Let's go there.
Okay,
let's see next over
here.  We are already recording.  Okay,
wait a minute.
Hm.  Look, it's not just a copy of the
website's structure anymore.  I, in fact, in
these in this JSON file that I have made, I have
not saved the structure, what I have
saved is the data of the web, which is
here.
Okay, this just has the data,
right?  Not the structure anymore.  What it has
is the data model, yes, that is,
the structure of the data model, but
not the structure of the website.  So
the idea is that when you make a
website, if you mix JSON and
content and CSS and all that, you end up with
, let's say, a bit of a hodgepodge,
everything together at once, right?  in the
same file.  And that's fine when you make a
single website, but when you make
many websites, having everything
together and everything mixed together means
reuse is much less.  So,
not just the articles in JSON, but output
the data to an external file, JSON,
XML, CSV, whatever you want, okay?  But
JSON is usually the most common.  What it
helps us do is separate the layers of
information and separate the
programming structure from the data.  And in this
way, uh, for example, the first
teaching unit, the one on recognizing the
characteristics of
markup languages, was very difficult because it was
an XML.  And why do I want an XML?
So now, in both markup languages
and programming, we're going to see
what we want XMLs for and what we want them
for, to store data, okay?  And
that's the answer to your question,
Sandro, okay?  We want the
Joneses to store data, to absorb,
to consume data on the web.  Okay?
Okay, so
I come over here to
computer systems and of course, of course, right?  But it's not that it makes
more sense because
I'm explaining it to you now, but
the more classes progress and
the more exercises we do,
the more we'll use JSON data consumption,
and that
's when you'll really see its meaning
and usefulness in the practical exercises.  Okay?  Well,
let's go to update
and of course, you know, let's open
Virtual Box, let's open the
virtual machine, let's open, well,
we had Ubuntu Server, right?  Or what?  I just do
n't remember anymore.  That is, we were
working on Ubuntu with the server or with
the normal one.  I think with the server, right?
Oh, I don't know.  Right now I don't know.
We were working with a Linux
server.  Okay, correct.
Okay.
Okay, so I open up here,
start the server.   Let's
go there.
Very good.  I enter as José Vicente.
Password of Atame a 23.
Okay.  And I have this here.  And once
I do this too, remember that this
was the virtual machine, I opened the normal Ubuntu
by mistake.  What do you mean by mistake?
No, I guess I'll have it there for some
other group of students, but oh well, it's
okay.  Okay, so now I
go to the monitor,
here I do an IF config, I see that I am
number 78.
Okay,
yes, that's why I'm telling you, but with you I
have opened, with you I have created the
server or the normal one.   I
say this to make sure we're
all on the same page.
Ah, with you just the normal one.  Okay,
as I mentioned before,
you made the server for me.  Okay, okay, then I'll
turn it off.  Hey, sudo shutdown.
Now you'll see that what I'm going to teach you
is basically the same,
right?  And give me a 2 3. Yeah, calm down,
calm down, nothing's wrong.  Okay.  And now
here in the Virtual Box I open the normal one.
Okay.
No. Oh, but then it was the server or it
was the normal one.
Okay, it was the server.  Okay, come on,
let's open the server.  So,
I close this one, I turn off the machine,
okay?  And we start the server.  Wait,
because now the server will be
running.  Okay, control C. All right.
Okay.  And now I was saying it was 78.
Okay, I say SSH Josévicente
@192168178.
I say yes and enter the password.  Give me a
23.
Hey, what happened?  What happened?  What
happened?  Just a moment.  Oh, the
system is shutting down
or something.  Yes. At one point the system
was scheduled to shut down.  Okay,
I'm going to start it again.
U to server.   Let's
go there.
Moment.
Okay, let's start the server and now,
from a terminal,
okay?  Forks.  And
this,
okay?  We do it like this.  I'm going to copy this for you
.
Okay, okay.  This is 001 login on the
server dot well MD,
right?
Login to the MD server.
Okay, what have I done?  Well, what I've
done is simply log into the
server.  Now once I get into the
server, we're going to see different types
of updates.  001
update
of eh
version packages.
MD.
To update the versions, let's
make this big.  You have to put sudo
apt update.  And when you put sudo update
update,
we'll see, eh, you should have virtual
box to test the to server.  Of
course, of course, because remember
that, and I'll take this opportunity to remind you,
remember that the methodology of the
classes is that everything I do, you
have to do the same,
okay?  Because most likely
everything I do will
appear in the activities.  So
if I start a point server, then most
likely later in the activities you will have
an install a point server
and enter this command and tell me what appears on the
screen and check that you have done I don't know
what, okay?  Therefore, always, always,
always everything that I do,
you must also do, and then,
and then do the activities.
Okay, so remember the
other day what I told you about
all your code having to be in Gizub.
Now we'll talk about it later.  So
now that I'm inside W Server, I
'm going to put this command next.
Sudo aptword
un 2s 3, here, okay?  The system
is connecting
to update all the repositories
and
okay, downloading the package list,
okay?  And then, and then it tells us,
"Okay, doing this,
uh, let's see, wait a minute
, Serena, I got a
message that says before the end of
class I'm leaving at 3,
but I don't know what you mean. I mean, I'm
missing like a piece of a sentence.
Okay, tell me when you can. I
say this because I have the piece of before the
end of class that I'm leaving at
three.
Ah, okay. Ah, ah, yes, yes, yes. Correct,
correct. Now I'll tell you. Okay, very
good. I do this, I put to do this that I'm
going to do now and now I comment about the
github, correct? Okay, so now
next
I say 002 update packages
pun
and then from here I
can say sudo apt upgrade
okay and that's it. I
copy,
paste,
launch and it tells me, "Look,
all these packages can be updated.   Doing so will
download 284 megabytes
of files, which when decompressed will
result in 415 megabytes of
additional disk space.  Do you want to perform this
operation?  Yeah. Okay, I'm going to copy all of
this
and I'm not going to copy what's coming
next because it's going to be a lot in
1000 lines.   I
say yes, I hit enter and now
what it's going to do is that all the
packages I have to update are
going to be updated.  Okay?  This is
a massive update.  Now,
I'll explain how to do a
piece-by-piece update, step by
step.
While this is being done, which will
take a little while, I'm going to tell you what I
was telling you about GitHub.
Remember what I mentioned the other day:
just as I upload
everything to JitHub,
just as I mentioned in
development environments when I showed you how to install
JitHub, what I want is for all of
you to put all your code
into GitHub, into your
JitHub, and share it with me.  How do you
do that?  I'm going to put a
series of, let's see, new files here,
right?
Exercises
share with me the githubd.
Okay, what do you have to do?
Step number one, you have to sign
up for JH,
that is, you have to go to jithaub.com
and sign up, that is, if you are not
signed out, okay?  If you're not signed
up here, if you're not
registered, then click sign in.
Once you've registered and
effectively entered, you no longer need to enter
project codes, but rather codes for everything you do,
that is, within this methodology that
everything I do, you
have to do as well, a methodology I
've talked about in the emails I
've sent you since the beginning of the
course.  You are supposed to be
doing all the code that I do,
so now it's time to put it
on your Jithub and send it to me.  So,
as I was saying, you have to sign up
for JHub.  Two, you
must create one or more repositories
or a repository
with folders
or more repositories.
One for programming, one for
databases, okay?  I don't know, whatever you want.
Okay, then wait for me to save
this or I'll lose it.  Okay, then
you download
GitHub Desktop
to your machine.
Four.  You clone
the
created repository.  How do you clone?  It is cloned
in Ghub Desktop from File Clone
Repository, right?  And in file Clone
Repository you will see that they will appear, now
you will see for a moment, you will see that
the repositories that you have prepared will appear,
okay?  from file clone repository.
Five,
in Windows Explorer
you put all your code
in the cloned folder.
How do you know which folder is
cloned?  Well, at the time of cloning,
the folder in which you
are going to clone it appears there.  It will be in my documents,
in the HC2 folder of Shamp, I don't know,
wherever you want.  Okay, if you've already
cloned it, how do you know which folder
you're in?  then right click and show in
your file manager.  For those of you on
Windows, it will show you in Windows
Explorer directly.
Now, once you do that, if I
go, for example, and you see that today
I created new
files here in the D 2526 folder,
then I go to DAM 2526 and it tells me, "Hey,
you created new files today."  Okay,
so
once you've
copied the files,
you commit and push.  What is commit
plus push?  So we go to Jitub Desktop
and click on the commit button and then click on the
push button.  What push button is it?
Black or blue?  It doesn't matter, they're
both the same, okay?  With which you give it
push.
Comitipus and with that
you have uploaded your files
to Jithah.
What do you do next?
You share it with me
on jidha.com
18.
You enter
the repository.
In the repository.  Wait for me to log in
.  They will ask me for SMS.  Okay.
Oh, SMS.
Here messages
and Okay.  Okay.
And 6 37
946.
Okay, very good.  Hey, let's see.
So, next, you'll
go to settings,
go to settings at the
end of the top bar
and in collaborators
you go to collaborators
and manage access people
manage access
ad people
you add
invitation
for the user user
and that's it.  Okay?  So
the goal is that in the same way that
you of course have access to
all my code, I also need to
have access to your repositories
to periodically check how
you're uploading the code, how you're
working, everything that you do in
the same way that I do at the end of each
class, I do it here and I commit and I
push and I upload the news, so
the goal is that you also
gradually work in such a way
that there comes a time when I
enter your JithHub and I go here
to the Commit history and I see how
you're uploading little by little and how you're
working periodically and how you're
gradually progressing, okay?  So that's
it in one sentence, okay?  It's what I
was telling you before, that
over the next few days, since we're
a month away from the exams, over the
next few days you should be posting the
code, sharing it, for
example, look this morning
to see,
okay, what I'm going to receive, to see if I've
already received any of yours,
okay?  and
not yet, okay, I'll get this,
okay?  I will therefore receive messages like these
in which each of you
will invite me to your repositories.  I see I have
n't received any yet from
right now, which means,
well, not yet, okay?
So do it as soon as possible.
Now,
what I want to see is
that you are going to work on the code first,
and second, we are going to see, yes, look, an
example of a student repositories.  Well,
now you're going to see it, huh?  And we'll see.
Valentin magnet ver
.
Okay.  And a little
programming moment, no, not yet.
Okay, let's see.
H a ver Rot
Root databases.  A moment about
markup languages.
Wow, what a moment they shared it with me
this morning and it seems that it's
still there.
Let's see, Brian.
Well, I'm going to pick up
some of the previous nerds.
Wait and
see, Fabiana,
okay?  For example, this aspect could
have in this case databases,
markup languages, programming,
right?  Within programming, then
creating constructors, creating
classes, repetition structures,
right?  This is the structure that
a student's repository could have.  That is to
say, my recommendation is that you follow the
same structure that I follow, because the
structure that I follow is literally
the structure of the regulations.
But if you don't follow the structure that I
follow, but you follow a structure such
that when I enter I can see and understand
the content, then that's fine by me.  Okay?
So, if I see a student here who
has put databases,
markup languages, and programming and I see some
folders here, I say, "Cool, okay?"  And
apart from that, I'm going in, the names are
clear, I'm clicking and I see that everything makes
sense and that everything has something, okay?  And
that everything is correct, well that's fine by me.  What I
don't want is to go into a
student's repository and see
HTMLs, SQLs,
Pythons, and everything mixed up there without a name, and that's it.
Okay?  So, let's see.  Correct.
Okay, indeed, your
Jithub Adam folder so I can see and
so I can keep track of
each of you and see how you're doing effectively.
Okay, that's it.  And I'm telling you, and in the
same way that you see that I work
directly in the GitHub folder and
so every time I make modifications
automatically at the end of the class, all I have to
do is
click the submit changes button.  Well, I
recommend that you do the same, that
is, not only send your
DAM folder one to Jitha, but
also what you can
do next is start working in that
folder and in that way, when working in
that folder, each update that
you make at the moment that
you go to GitHub Desktop and you click
commit and push,
I will automatically have it, okay?  So that's the
idea, right?  Okay, then let's see.
And by the way, over the next few days I'll
send you a questionnaire just so you
can fill in the URL of your
repository so I can have it
saved there.  Okay?
Okay, so after doing
this, after a good while of
updating, okay?  I already have all
the updated versions within my
operating system.
In this case, in this case 003 dis
upgrade.   I'm
going to write this to you, but I'm not
going to recommend it to you.  Ok, I sweat aptade
when it's worth it, only for when the version
is very outdated.  I'm currently
using Ubuntu 2404,
long time support.
Let's say 2604 comes out
and I, for example,
to upgrade
from 2404 to 2604
or to put it another way, this is
like upgrading from Windows 10 to Windows
11, right?  so that you understand, let's say,
what the scope of what that
command does is.  The thing is that upgrading
from Windows 10 to Windows 11 is a
hassle, whereas with Linux it's a
single command, but I
don't recommend doing it.  I'm telling you that
this command exists, I'm not going to use it
because it would update the entire system and that
's not something I want to do right now.
What I recommend when I, for
example, have 2404, right now
on my server, the real one, and I know
this April, right?
Ubuntu
LTS will be released in April 2026 because it comes out every 2 years.  So
what I'll do when that time comes
is first wait until summer, okay?  And
around August 15th or so,
what I'll probably do is pull everything
off my server, reinstall it
from scratch, but with Ubuntu 2604,
and I'll reinstall everything.  Okay, it's the
same recommendation.  This is
a more personal recommendation than an
official one, but the same thing happens when I have to
upgrade a computer from Windows 10 to
Windows 11. My recommendation is not to
upgrade.  That is, my recommendation
is to go to Windows 10, extract all the
contents of the operating system, make
a copy on an external hard drive or a USB
drive, whatever you want, and
then format the computer and
install a clean Windows 11.  Okay?
That's my recommendation
for Windows, Linux,
Mac, and any
operating system.  Okay?  Now, now, once
we've talked about the operations in a
big way, okay?  Now
what we're going to do next are
package-by-package operations, that is, I don't
want to install everything in a huge way or
uninstall everything in a huge way, I want to have
a little more control.  Okay, let's see
what we can get.  So we already
saw the other day how to install the
MD package.  We already saw the other day that if
we want to install a program we need to run sudo
apt install, for example, APCH 2. Okay,
in this case I'm going to run it.  We know
that we already have Apache 2 installed, so
sudo app install 2 tells us that
in this case Apache is already
at its most recent version, it tells us,
"Hey, you already have it, you don't need to
install it."  Ok, but next I
want an install, so I
sudo appt un install or remove.  Oh,
right now I'm doubting AP2,
so sudót install remove and it tells
us, "Are 465 KB going to be freed
after this operation?"  Yes. Okay,
sure.  What's going on?  that I just
uninstalled, which means that if
I now
go to 192 168 178, there is
no more Apache because I have uninstalled
the application.  In fact, we have
uninstalled Apache so that we
can later run this test and it will show that
we have really removed Apache.  If
I want to reinstall Apache, I
just hit sudo app
install 2 again.
Okay.  And
okay.  Now, next
will update.
There are times when you run Apache or any other
application, I don't care, okay?  There are
times when, wait a minute, there are times when
we already have the application installed, but
we've had it installed for a while and what we
want is to update it.  So
sudo aptateche
2. What this command does
is connect to the server,
check if there's a newer version
of Apache than the one we have, and
update it.
Okay.  Uh, sorry, yeah, sudo apt.  Hello.
No, wait.
Uh,
no.  Accept arguments.  No. Mm.
UPT update application.  It's probably an
upgrade.
Let's see,
upgate, no.
Oh, okay.  Okay.
Okay, we say install,
okay?  and tells us, "It's already on the
latest version."  Okay, correct.
It's install APH 2 also
to update
to the next version or the latest
version or whatever.
Okay, with this we see how we are
able to, at any given time,
update and start up and do whatever we
want.  Now,
recovery of operating systems and
applications.  Okay, this is where
things get a little more complicated.
How do we recover?  What would you
say to me in the chat?  How do we recover
a crashed operating system?
What do you say?
There is a rule that is sacred, it is very
simple.  What do you say?
Sandro, that is the correct answer.  The
correct answer is
backup.  That is to say, there are multiple
ways for an operating system to
crash,
but it depends on the disaster that
occurs in the operation, let's say,
recovery, because it may be that the
only solution to recover an
operating system is to restore the
backup that was previously made
if a backup was made.
So to do this I'm going to do the
following.  Let's see.  In this case, since I
installed Apache, let's see
what I have, let's see it here.  Just a
sec, I'm going to make a
backup, but I need 5
minutes first.
I'm going to leave this open.  I'm going to stop
recording.  Of course, do you remember
what we did the other day to create a
backup of the database
from MySQL?  We're going to do something
similar today.